World Federation of Trade Unions Records 5595
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
World Federation of Trade Unions Records
1945-1973
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
World Federation of Trade Unions (WFTU)
5595
4 cubic feet
4 linear ft.
Correspondence, minutes, proceedings.
This collection consists of records of the World Federation of Trade Union's conferences, including agendas, reports, and speeches. Included is an index.
5667727
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, October 11, 2012
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, June 05, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The World Federation of Trade Unions (WFTU) was founded at a world labor conference in London, England in 1945. Its stated goal was the development of better understanding and joint programs among the national unions of various countries. The WFTU soon came under the control of affiliated communist unions. Communist domination of the WFTU resulted in the disaffiliation of the Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) in 1949. The CIO then joined with other labor organizations opposed to the politics of the WFTU to form the International Confederation of Free Trade Unions.
Scope and Contents
Records consist primarily of the minutes, proceedings and reports of WFTU officers and governance committees, produced and presented at WFTU conferences held in London (1945, 1949); Paris (1945, 1947, 1949); Moscow (1946, 1970); Trieste (1946); Prague (1947, 1958, 1963, 1967); Geneva (1948); Rome (1948); Peking (1949); Budapest (1950, 1969, 1972); Bucharest (1950, 1971); Berlin (1951, 1958); Vienna (1951-1953); Warsaw (1954, 1959); Sofia (1956, 1966); Nicosia (1966); Khartoum (1970); and Varna (1973). Also include some personal correspondence and WFTU materials collected by Adolf F. Germer (socialist; official and organizer of the Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) and various coal and petroleum workers' unions) during his attendance as the CIO delegate to the WFTU conference (Prague, 1946), and his membership on the WFTU Committee on German Affairs (1947).
Governance records (1945-1973) include minutes, resolutions and proceedings of the WFTU Executive Bureau, General Councils, and committees (1945-1973) and of joint meetings of the WFTU and International Trade Secretariats (1948); also financial statements of the WFTU (1945-1949).
Reports and publications (1946-1973) consist mainly of unpublished reports and some pamphlets produced and presented at the annual sessions of the Executive Bureau and General Councils of the WFTU; also reports pertaining to special policies and activities of the WFTU. Materials pertaining to the WFTU's internal organization discuss or document the creation of WFTU international trade departments and negotiations between WFTU and International Trade Secretariats (1947-1948); establishment of WFTU departments on professionals, metal trades workers, miners, textile workers, and agricultural and forestry workers (1946-1964); charter of union rights (1954); and various revisions and amendments to the WFTU constitution (1948-1970). Also include documents regarding relations between the WFTU and the United Nations, International Labour Organization, Congress of Industrial Organizations, American Federation of Labor, and Allied Commission (Berlin); and various conferences, including the Pan Asiatic Trade Union Conference, the Pan Africa Conference, and the World Trade Union Congress (1948-1973).
Also, WFTU policy statements regarding union activity and socioeconomic conditions in Spain, Iran, Egypt, South Africa, Greece, Occupied Germany and various colonial countries (1946); activities in Trieste, Tunisia, Iran, Japan, Austria, the international coal countries, Greece and Portugal (1947-1948); in Burma, Italy, Israel, and Japan (1949-1952); and in the European coal and steel community, Vietnam, colonial and newly independent countries, and Palestine (1953-1965).
Additional reports (some of which were produced by WFTU officers Louis Saillant, Leon Jouhaux, S. Rostovsky, Fernando Santi and R. Vivimari) regard WFTU policy on: professional workers, migrations, postwar reconstruction and grants-in-aid, equal work and equal wages for women workers, and union rights (1946-1948); racial discrimination, currency devaluations, the international labor movement, and the WFTU delegation to Israel (1949-1950); social security, struggles for political and union rights for international workers (1951-1952); atomic war and peace, women workers and young workers (1953-1958); and the European Economic Community and monopolies, protection of victims of anti-union repression, and general WFTU activities (1959-1966); also, international union relations, unions and scientific and technical progress, unity among unions, monetary crises, economic and social demands of workers in capitalist
countries, and union education (1967-1973).
Additional documents collected by Adolf F. Germer (CIO delegate to the WFTU) include various bulletins and press releases of the U.S. military government in Germany; pamphlets and reports pertaining to the trade union movement, social welfare, women workers, and political issues in Czechoslovakia (1945-1947); and press releases and publications of the Freier Deutscher Gewerkschaftsbund.
Also, a file of correspondence between Germer and various WFTU leaders, American union leaders and politicians. Correspondents include Philip Murray (president, CIO); Louis Saillant (general secretary, WFTU); William Green (president, American Federation of Labor); Wayne Morse (U.S. senator) and Leon Blum (prime minister of France). The correspondence generally pertains to WFTU conferences, publications, development of international unionism, and relations between unions and the WFTU (1944-1947).
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5256: Adolph Germer Papers 5396 mf: World Federation of Trade Unions Reports and Minutes on Microfilm
Anti-unionism; Coal mining -- Europe; Collective bargaining -- Professions; Working class -- Economic conditions; Steel industry and trade -- Europe; Agricultural laborers -- Labor unions -- International cooperation; Coal-miners -- Labor unions -- International cooperation; Foresters -- Labor unions -- International cooperation; Metal-workers -- Labor unions -- International cooperation; Miners -- Labor unions -- International cooperation; Textile workers -- Labor unions -- International cooperation; Workers' education; Solidarity; Labor unions; Blum, Leon, 1872-1950; Germer, Adolph; Green, William, 1872-1952; Jouhaux, Leon, 1879-1954; Morse, Wayne.; Murray, Philip, 1886-1952.; Rostovsky, S.; Saillant, Louis.; Santi, Fernando.; Vivimari, R.; Allied Commission; American Federation of Labor; Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.); International Labour Organization; Pan Africa Conferences; Pan Asiatic Trade Union Conference; United Nations; World Federation of Trade Unions; World Trade Union Congress
5667727
- Federation Syndicale Mondial (FSM): Reunion du Bureau Syndicale, 1945-10-06-1945-10-09 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  30 page mimeographed typescript
- Federation Syndicale Mondial (FSM): Reunion du Bureau Executif (Box 1, Folder 1)
  21 page mimeographed typescript
- Federation Syndicale Mondiale: Session du Bureau Executif (Box 1, Folder 2)
  29 page mimeographed typescript
- Federation Syndicale Mondiale: Rapport au Bureau Executif de la FSM sur la representation de la FSM au sien del Organisation des Nations Unies (ONU) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  15 page mimeographed typescript
- Federation Syndicale Mondiale: Reports on trade departments presented to the Executive Bureau-Paris-1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  26 page mimeographed typescript
- Session of the Executive Committee, 1946-06-22-1946-06-27 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  106 page mimeographed typescript
- Session of the Executive Bureau, 1946-06-17-1946-06-20 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  80 page mimeographed typescript
- Report of the commission of the WFTU to investigate conditions in Germany adopted by the Executive Bureau in Moscow, 1946-06-17-1946-06-20 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  63 page mimeographed typescript
- [Provisional] Report of the commission of the WFTU to investigate conditions in Germany, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  73 page mimeographed typescript
- Report on the position, the activity and the decisions of the World Trade Union Movement with regard to the struggle against the dictatorship of General Franco in Spain - Presented to the Executive Bureau and the Executive Committee of the WFTU, 1946-06-17-1946-06-20 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  13 page mimeographed typescript
- Report on the relations between the World Federation of Trade Unions (WFTU) and the Inter-Allied Control Council in Berlin - Presented to the Executive Bureau and the Executive Committee of the WFTU, 1946-06 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  16 page mimeographed typescript
- Report on the internal organization of departments of the WFTU - Presented to the Executive Committee of the WFTU, 1946-06-17-1946-06-20 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  9 page mimeographed typescript
- Report on the creation of the International Trade Departments presented to the executive Bureau and Executive Committee of the WFTU, 1946-06 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  25 page mimeographed typescript
- Report on the imprisonment of Comrade el Hedarrek member of the General Council of the WFTU and on the restrictions imposed on the exercise of trade union rights in Egypt - Presented to the Executive Committee of the WFTU, 1946-06 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  6 page mimeographed typescript
- Report on the help of the WFTU to the trade unions in colonial countries or mandated territories - Presented by the General Secretary of the WFTU to the Executive Bureau and Executive Committee, 1946-06 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Report of the representation of the WFTU within the United Nations Organization - Presented by the General Secretary to the Executive Committee of the WFTU, 1946-06 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  48 page mimeographed typescript
- Memorandum on the creation of the activity and admission to the WFTU of the Greek General Federation of Labor- Presented to the Executive bureau and Executive Committee of the WFTU, 1946-06 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  11 page mimeographed typescript
- Session of the Executive Bureau, 1946-09-20-1946-09-24 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  90 page mimeographed typescript
- Report of the General Secretary of the WFTU on his mission of Iran-Presented to the Executive Bureau of the WFTU, 1946-09 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  18 page mimeographed typescript
- Report of the Commission of Enquiry on Tunisia - Presented to the Executive Bureau, 1946-09 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  7 page mimeographed typescript
- Report from Mr. Verret concerning his delegation at the 5th Session of the UNRA Council in Geneva - Presented to the Executive Bureau of the WFTU, 1946-09 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  5 page mimeographed typescript
- Report concerning the representation of the WFTU at the United Nations Food and Agricultural Organisation - Presented to the Executive Bureau of the WFTU, 1946-09 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  4 page mimeographed typescript
- Rapport concernant les refugees at les personnes deplacees presente au Bureau Executif de la FSM, 1946-09 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Report by Leon Jouhaux, Vice-President of the WFTU on his visit to Greece to the Executive Bureau of the WFTU, 1946-09 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  19 page mimeographed typescript
- Report concerning the relations of the WFTU with the Allied Control Council in Berlin since the session of the Executive Committee of June 1946 - Presented to the Executive Bureau of the WFTU, 1946-09 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Report on the representation of the World Federation of Trade Unions (WFTU) within the United Nations Organization (UNO) - Presented by the General Secretary to the Executive Bureau of the WFTU, 1946-09 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  20 page mimeographed typescript
- Report on the meeting of the Trade Unions of Trieste, 1946-10-18-1946-10-20 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  32 page mimeographed typescript
- Session of the Executive Bureau, 1946-12-09-1946-12-16 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  152 page mimeographed typescript
- Report on the representation of the WFTU within the UNO - Presented by the General Secretary to the Executive Bureau o the WFTU, 1946-12 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  14 page mimeographed typescript
- Report on the strike of the South African Miners, 1946-12 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Provisional report of the 2nd WFTU Enquiry Commission on the Situation in Germany, 1947-01-1947-02 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  88 page mimeographed typescript
- Report on migrations, 1947-01-09-1947-01-10 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  51 page mimeographed typescript
- Report on the fact-finding mission to Africa, 1947-02-1947-04 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  78 page mimeographed typescript
- General Secretary's report on the WFTU enquiry in Japan, 1947-03-1947-04 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  107 page mimeographed typescript
- Report on visit to Greece, 1947-04-26-1947-05-03 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Sessions of the Executive Bureau held in Prague, 1947-06-02-1947-06-15 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Session of the Executive Committee, 1947-06-06-1947-06-07 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Trade Union situation in Iran, report of the delegation of the WFTU to Iran - Presented to the Executive Bureau Executive Committee and General Council, 1947-06-02-1947-06-14 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  33 page mimeographed typescript
- Reports on the trade union situation in Tunisia - Report of T. McWhinnie on the first Congress of the UGTT - Report of Mustapha el Kriss on his trade union inquiry - Presented to the Executive Bureau and Committee, 1947-06-02-1947-06-07 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  43 page mimeographed typescript
- Report on the Trade Union situation in Trieste- Presented to the Executive Bureau, Executive Committee and General Council, 1947-06-02-1947-06-14 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  8 page mimeographed typescript
- Inquiry, Conference and Resolutions concerning the situation in Austria - Report presented to the Executive Bureau, Executive Committee and General Council, 1947-06-02-1947-06-14 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  57 page mimeographed typescript
- Pan-African Trade Union Information Conference: Report and conclusions - Presented to the Executive Bureau, Executive Committee and General Council, 1947-06-02-1947-06-14 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Draft preliminary report of the delegation to Japan and Korea, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  23 page mimeographed typescript
- Situation of the coal industry in the world, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  120 page mimeographed typescript
- Minutes of the joint meeting of the delegation of the Executive Bureau of the WFTU with the Advisory Committee of the ITS, 1947-08-19 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Session of the Executive Bureau, 1947-11-18-1947-11-24 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  124 page mimeographed typescript
- Executive Bureau - Statement on the Trade Union situation in Germany, 1947-11-18-1947-11-24 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Federation Syndicale Mondiale (FSM): Note-Concernant le probleme des departments professionals - Presente au Bureau Executif, 1947-11-18-1947-11-24 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Introductory report on the relation between the WFTU and the I.L.O. - Presented to the Executive Bureau, 1947-11-18-1947-11-24 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Report on the 5th session of the Economic and Social Council of the U.N.O. - Presented to the Executive Bureau, 1947-11-18-1947-11-24 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  28 page mimeographed typescript
- Supplement to the report of the Trade Department of the WFTU, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Conclusions, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Addition to the conclusions of the report about Germany, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  1 page mimeographed typescript
- Note for the information of members of the Executive Bureau, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- session of the Executive Bureau, 1948-04-30-1948-05-02 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  61 page mimeographed typescript
- Report on the trade union situation in Germany - Presented to the Executive Bureau and Executive Committee of the WFTU, 1948-04-30-1948-05-02 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Report on the activity of the WFTU concerning the principles of equality of wages for equal work between male and female labour. Submitted to the Executive Bureau and Committee of the WFTU, 1948-05-02 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  37 page mimeographed typescript
- Report on the trade union situation in Greece. Submitted to the Executive Bureau and Committee of the WFTU, 1948-04-30-1948-05-02 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  22 page mimeographed typescript
- Report on negotiations between the ILO and the WFTU. Submitted to the Executive Board and Committee of the WFTU, 1948-04-30-1948-05-02 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Notice for the members of the Executive Committee, Rome, 1968-05 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Report on the creation of the Trade Departments. Submitted to the Executive Bureau and Committee of the WFTU, 1948-04-30-1948-05-02 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Report on the relations between the WFTU with the Economic Council of UNO. Submitted to the Executive Bureau and Committee of the WFTU, 1948-04-30-1948-05-02 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Report on the activities of the WFTU in connection with the guarantee of exercise and extension of trade union rights. Submitted to the Executive Bureau and Committee of the WFTU, 1948-04-30-1948-05-02 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Session of the executive Committee, 1948-05-05-1948-05-10 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  136 page mimeographed typescript
- Report concerning breaches of trade union right submitted to the United Nations Economic and Social Council by the WFTU, 1948-06 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  35 page mimeographed typescript
- Session of the Executive Bureau, 1948-09-17-1948-09-21 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  103 page mimeographed typescript
- Joint meeting of the WFTU Executive Bureau and the representatives of the ITS, 1948-09-14-1948-09-16 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- For the meeting of the Executive Bureau - Item 9 of the draft agenda - Information concerning the work of the members of the Commission of Enquiry to Japan, 1948-09 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- For the meeting of the Executive Bureau - Point 7 of the draft agenda - Report on the trade union situation in Germany, 1948-09 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  40 page mimeographed typescript
- For the session of the Executive Bureau - Item 3 of the draft agenda - Note on the decision and correspondence concerning a Pan-Asiatic Trade Union Conference, 1948-09 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- For the meeting of the Executive Bureau - Item 4 of the draft agenda - Report on the seventh session of the Economic Aid and Social Council, 1948-09 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- For the meeting of the Executive Bureau - Point 5 of the draft agenda - Draft concerning a Trade Union Conference on Hygiene, Security at Work and Health Policy, 1948-09 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- For the meeting of the Executive Bureau - Item 12 on the draft agenda - Communication from the General Secretary on the trade union situation in Mexico and Latin America, 1948-09 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Economic and Social Services. Documentary note on post-war reconstruction and economic aid, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  167 page mimeographed typescript
- Session of the executive Bureau, 1949-01-17-1949-01-22 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Session of Executive Committee, 1949-01-26-1949-02-01 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  188 page mimeographed typescript
- Letter from the General Secretary to the affiliated national centers re incidents at January 19 session of the Executive Bureau, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  10 page mimeographed typescript
- Executive Bureau of the WFTU - Item I of the draft agenda - Report of the implementation of the decisions and resolutions of the 2nd World Trade Union Congress, 1949-11-11-1949-11-14 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Executive Bureau of the WFTU - Item II of the draft agenda - Report on the International Day for Peace on October 2, 1949-11-11-1949-11-14 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Executive Bureau of the WFTU - Item III of the draft agenda - Report on the Trade Departments, 1949-11-11-1949-11-14 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  12 page mimeographed typescript
- Executive Bureau of the WFTU - Item IV of the draft agenda - Report on the tasks and activities of the WFTU at UNO and specialized agencies, 1949-11-11-1949-11-14 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Executive Bureau of the WFTU - Item VII of the draft agenda - Report on the devaluation, 1949-11-11-1949-11-14 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Report on social and economic discrimination against workers for reasons of race or color (report sent to the UN Secretary General on December 13, 1949, to be inserted on the agenda of the 10th session of the Economic and Social Council), 1949-12 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  47 page mimeographed typescript
- Executive Committee meeting - Point 4 of the draft agenda - General report of information on the activity of the WFTU since the Lind World Trade Union Conference, 1950-05-19-1950-05-24 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  145 page mimeographed typescript
- Executive Committee meeting - Point 9 of the draft agenda - The tasks and methods of the WFTU's propaganda work - Rapporteur: S. Rostovsky, Secretary, WFTU, 1950-05-19-1950-05-24 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  67 page mimeographed typescript
- Executive committee meeting - Speech of Comrade Rostovsky on the tasks and methods of the WFTU's propaganda work, 1950-05-19-1950-05-24 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Executive Committee meeting - Report by the Executive Bureau on the attitude of the Central Council of the Trade Unions of Yugoslavia - Point 3 of the draft agenda, 1950-05-19-1950-05-24 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Executive Committee meeting - The problems of unemployment and full employment - Point 6 of the draft agenda, 1950-05-19-1950-05-24 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  36 page mimeographed typescript
- Executive Committee meeting - Report of the consultative conference of the Trade Unions Internationals (trade departments of the WFTU) - Rapporteur: B. Gebert, Secretary of the WFTU - Point 9 of the draft agenda, 1950-05-19-1950-05-24 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Executive Committee - Activity and tasks of the WFTU in the fight for trade union unity - Rapporteur: B. Frachon, France - Point 6 of the draft agenda, 1950-05-19-1950-05-24 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  24 page mimeographed typescript
- WFTU Executive Bureau meeting - Item 2 - Administration of the trade department and creation of new ones - Situation of the Metal Workers Trade Department - Rapporteur: H. Jourdain, 1950-12-01-1950-12-07 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Executive Bureau meeting - Item 2 - Administration of the trade union departments and creation of new ones - Situation of the Maritime and Port Worker's Trade Union International - Rapporteur: A. Fressinet, 1950-12-01-1950-12-07 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- WFTU Executive Bureau meeting - Item 3 - WFTU Review - 'World Trade Union Movement' - Rapporteur: S Rostovsky, 1950-12-01-1950-12-07 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Meeting of the Executive Bureau of the WFTU - Item 4 - Report on the trade union situation in Africa - Rapporteur: A. Dialio, 1950-12-01-1950-12-07 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- WFTU Executive Bureau meeting - Item 7 - Information for Trade Union Centres a) proposal from the Pancrypian Federation of Labor, 1950-12-01-1950-12-07 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- WFTU Executive Bureau meeting - Item 7 - Information for Trade Union Centres c) decision of the General Council of Histradrut (State of Israel), 1950-12-01-1950-12-07 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- WFTU Executive Bureau meeting - Item 7 - Information for Trade Union Centres d) Statement on the Secretariats conversations with the representative of the Burmese unions, 1950-12-01-1950-12-07 (Box 2, Folder 25)